Medicine Collection, 1845-1920
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Medicine collection
1826-1972
MS 453
9 boxes; 8 volumes (4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection is comprised entirely of printed materials such as bibliographies, biographies, pamphlets, and articles pertaining to women in the field of medicine, including physicians, nurses, and medical missionaries. Women's hospital, colleges, and medical societies are also documented.
The Medicine Collection is comprised entirely of printed materials such as bibliographies, biographies, pamphlets, articles, and books pertaining to women in all fields of medicine. The collection dates from 1826 to 1972. Materials on women physicians, nurses, and medical missionaries include mostly biographical information on individuals such as Elizabeth and Emily Blackwell, Edith Cavell, Alice Hamilton, Mary Putnam Jacobi, Florence Nightingale, and Mary Walker. The Physicians section also includes files on countries other than the U.S. Files on women's hospital, colleges, and medical societies include primarily published material related to specific institutions in the U.S. and Great Britain. There two boxes of bulletins from the Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania. There is also general material related to women in the health professions.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania-- History--Sources; Medical education--United States--History--Sources; Medicine--History--Sources; Medicine--Societies, etc.--History--Sources; Missionaries, Medical--History--Sources; Nurses--History--Sources; Women in medicine--History--Sources; Women medical students--History--Sources; Women physicians--History--Sources; Women's hospitals--History--Sources
- Physicians
  - Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Countries (not U.S.)
    - General: "Les femmes docteurs en medecine dans tous les pays" by Haryette Fontanges, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Australia (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Canada (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - China (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - England
      - Biographies (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - Phipson, Edith Pechey (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - France (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Germany (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Greenland (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - India (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Italy (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Japan (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Latin America (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Netherlands (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Scotland (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Thailand (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - United States
    - General
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Articles, 1895-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Pamphlets, 1850-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - States: women in medicine, Kansas, New York, South (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Biographical materials
      - General: articles on women doctors (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Baker, Sara Josephine (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Baumgartner, Leona (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Blackwell, Elizabeth (Box 2, Folder 27)
        [See also Books on Shelf]
      - Blackwell, Emily (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Bradley, Frances Sage (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Call, Emma (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - DeVoll, Sarah Wood (Howard) (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Hahn, Pearl (Box 2, Folder 31a)
      - Hamilton, Alice (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Jacobi, Mary Putnam (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Mosher, Eliza M. (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Pierson, Mary Wright (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Pratt, Elsie Seelye (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Spock, Benjamin (Box 2, Folder 36a)
      - Standish, Hilda Crosby (Box 2, Folder 36b)
      - Tracy, Martha (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Walker, Mary Edwards (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - White, Priscilla (Box 2, Folder 38a)
  - Medical missionaries
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Biographies
      - Beals, Rose Fairbanks (Box 3, Folder 39a)
      - Berry, Katherine F.: Katie-San by Berry, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Dyer, Lora Genevieve (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - [File missing] (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Nurses and nursing
  - General
    - Wide Neighborhoods by Mary Breckinridge (Box 3)
      [See Books on Shelf]
    - Pamphlets and articles, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Biographical materials
    - Cavell, Edith (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Delano, Jane A. (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Dock, Lavinia (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Hancock, Cornelia (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Geller, Anne Dravo vanKirk (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Kells, Maud V. (Box 4, Folder 48a)
    - Low, Sarah (Box 4, Folder 48b)
    - Maass, Clara (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Nightingale, Florence (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Nutting, Mary Adelaide (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Army nurses (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Black nurses (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Frontier Nursing Service, Inc., Louisville, KY (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Countries (not U.S.)
    - General: pamphlets and articles (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - England: Liverpool Nurses Training School (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Japan (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Health professions
  - General: pamphlets (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Conferences: reports of proceedings
    - Women's Leadership and Authority in the Health Professions, UC Santa Cruz, 19-21 Jun 1977 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - International Conference on Women in Health, Washington D.C., 16-18 June 1975 (Box 5)
- Hospitals
  - American Women's Hospital Service (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - L'Hopital Sainte Justine, Montreal (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - New York Infirmary (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - St. Louis Children's Hospital (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Uplands Sanatorium, Pleasant Hill, Tennessee (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Vincent Memorial Hospital. "The Vincent Show" (Box 6)
  - Women's Institute of New York City, 1872 (Box 6, Folder 65)
- Medical Schools and Societies
  - Medical Schools
    - General (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - United States (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous: articles (Box 7, Folder 67)
      - Johns Hopkins Medical School (Box 7, Folder 68)
      - New England Female Medical College/Female Medical Education Society (Boston) (Box 7, Folder 69)
        [See also New England Hospital Records, SSC]
      - Women's College of Physicians and Surgeons of the City of New York (Box 7, Folder 70)
      - Women's Medical College of Baltimore (Box 7, Folder 70a)
      - Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania (Box 7, Folder 71)
        [See also Box 8]
    - England: medical schools and organizations (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Medical Societies
    - American Medical Women's Association (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Massachusetts Medical Society (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Medical Women's International Association. (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Medical Women's National Association (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - New England Women's Medical Society (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - "Women's physicians and their state medical societies" article by Phoebe Peck (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Philadelphia Medical Society (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Women's Medical Association of New York City (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania: Bulletins, 1889-1960 (Box 8-9)
- Books on Shelf
  - The Annual of Allentown Nurses College, Vol. VII 1926
  - Alsop, Gulielma. History of the Woman's Medical College, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1850-1950 Philadelphia, 1950
  - Blackwell, Elizabeth, M.D. Address on the Medical Education of Women 1856
  - Breckenridge, Mary. Wide Neighborhoods, a story of the Frontier Nursing Service. New York, 1952
  - Lutzker, Edyth. Women Gain a Place in Medicine. New York, 1969
  - Thoms, Adah B. Pathfinders: a history of the progress of colored graduate nurses. New York, 1929
  - Nursing School Today and Tomorrow. Final report of the Committee on the Grading of Nursing Schools. New York, 1934
  - McLaren, Eva Shaw. A History of the Scottish Women's Hospitals. London, 1919
- Oversize Materials
  - Poster: "Send Us a Lady Physician" (Map-case Flat File)